（改編自艾薩克阿西莫夫的小說）
曾經有一個男人 拜訪哈里謝頓 請他告知自己的命運
Once, a man came to Hari Seldon and asked to be told his fate.
他想知道
He wanted to know
預測模型是否能測量他人生的重要性
whether the predictive models could chart the significance of his life.
但哈里告訴他 只有一群人的行為能被預測
But Hari told him only the movements of masses could be predicted.
個人的命運將永遠是一個謎
The fate of one individual will always remain a mystery.
文明的構造
The clockwork of civilization…
文化的興起與消亡
the rise and fall of cultures…
因果與世界
causes and worlds…
對于這些問題 哈里謝頓早已解開謎底
These were answers Hari Seldon had long since unriddled.
信仰是一種強大的武器
Belief is a powerful weapon.
正因如此 帝國才這么忌憚哈里的預測
That's why the Empire feared Hari Seldon's predictions so much.
大帝們統治著世俗事物 但身后事呢 我們的靈魂呢
Empires govern worldly concerns, but what comes after? Our souls?
這些屬于信仰范疇
These realms are the purview of faith.
而信仰是在永恒之火中鑄造的寶劍
And faith is a sword forged in the fires of the infinite.
大帝 你需要換種娛樂嗎
Empire? Do you seek different amusement?
你就足夠了 常規的方式、常規的歡愉
You'll do. For the routine pleasures in the routine manner.
你喜歡哪種歡愉 大帝
Which pleasures do you prefer, Empire?
你能提供虛無的歡愉嗎 那有可能嗎
Do you offer the pleasure of nothing? Is that on the menu?
他們說的是真的嗎 誰都不能碰你
Is it true? No one's allowed to touch you?
你的膽子挺大的啊
Bold, aren't you?
我只有24個小時來服侍你 我想好好利用
I have only 24 hours of service to you. I want to make the most of it.
那你試一下觸摸我吧
Then try to touch me.
我讓你試一下
I said try.
光環能阻擋動能
The aura repels kinetic energy.
再試一次 這一次動作輕柔一點
I want you to try it again, with a softer touch.
慢一點
Slower.
那么…
So, how…
其他部分呢
…does the rest work?
怎么了
What?
有事需要你務必出席 大帝
You are required, Empire.
我明白大帝此刻有肢體親密接觸的需求
I understand Empire has a physiological need for intimacy.
但當前事宜的重要性超出這一需求
But the current matter supersedes this need.
使者贊沃
Ambassador Thanwall.
至高無上的大帝 榮耀之光…
Most esteemed Empire, glory to the light--
有話直說吧 使者
Out with it, Ambassador.
比鄰星教宗歐珀去世了 大帝
Proxima Opal has passed, Empire.
節哀
Our condolences.
節哀 真誠致哀
Condolences. Heartfelt.
謝謝 大帝
Thank you, Empire.
比鄰星教宗歐珀的教眾將懷念及哀悼她
Proxima Opal will be missed and mourned by her flock.
主教團將提拔她的繼任者瑪澤菲爾格拉特
And now the conclave will elevate her successor, Zephyr Gilat.
一位有能力的候選人 我們喜歡她
A capable candidate. We like her.
使者 請轉達我們的哀悼
Carry our condolences forward, Ambassador.
并告知格拉特 川陀永遠歡迎她的來臨
And inform Gilat she's always welcome on Trantor.
關于繼任者 大帝
On the topic of a successor, Empire,
存在一些爭議
there is some debate.
另一位候選人的呼聲頗高
Another candidate has been gaining support.
澤菲爾哈利瑪
Zephyr Halima.
哈利瑪伊法不遵從既成的教規
Halima Ifa does not adhere to accepted doctrine,
與過去的比鄰星教宗不同
as have our previous proximas.
她倡導回到《元八開經》
She is advocating for a return to the Primary Octavo.
她是自尋死路嗎
Is she suicidal?
這女人是誰 膽敢質疑我們的根基
Who is this woman to question our primacy?
請恕罪 大帝 我…
A-A-Apologies, Empire. I-I--
-你知道這事嗎  -剛剛才知道
-Did you know about this? -Only moments ago.
歐珀的葬禮是什么時候
When is Opal's funeral?
兩天后 大帝
Two days hence, Empire.
不要對他人提及今天的對話 我們很快會聯系你
Say nothing of this conversation. We will contact you shortly.
前任比鄰星教宗上位時 是我提供了幫助
I helped install the previous Proxima.
我會盡快去和主教團見面
I'll leave for the conclave as soon as possible.
這有必要嗎 你不能用全息影像聯絡
Is that really necessary? Can't you just holo-cast yourself in?
這次不行
Not this time.
透光教有三萬億教徒 這次教會分裂需要我親身處理
Luminism claims three trillion followers. This schism requires a personal touch.
《元八開經》是什么
What's the Primary Octavo?
是異教徒的經文 帝國前時代的
A heretical scripture. Pre-imperial.
它將靈魂與個人知覺連結起來
It directly links the soul to individuated sentience.
-那是什么… -個人知覺
-What does that mean-- -Individuated sentience.
思考 黎明兄弟
Think, Brother Dawn.
如果靈魂僅與一個獨立個體有關
If a soul cleaves only to an individual being,
那么人們會質疑沒有個體性的事物
that calls into question that which cannot be individuated.
所有克里昂大帝 都是一世的完美基因復刻品
All Cleons are perfect genetic copies of the first.
因此…
And therefore…
我們沒有靈魂
We don't have souls.
所以這個叫哈利瑪的女人是說我們…
So, this Halima woman is saying we're, what?
沒有人性
Not human?
間接的意思是這樣 但…
Indirectly. But--
如果星系的民眾開始認為
And if the galaxy comes to believe
領袖不如他們 而不是比他們更優越
their leaders are less than, rather than more than themselves,
民眾也許不會再追隨帝國
they may cease to follow.
我們是一艘玻璃船
We are a glass vessel…
由一只靈巧的手控制
spun with a fine hand.
如果內部壓力開始紊亂并且我們不團結
If the pressures inside start to swirl and we are not uniform…
我們也許會爆炸
we may burst.
-你是誰  -塞佛哈定
-Who are you? -Salvor Hardin.
端點星的守衛者
Warden of Terminus.
安納克里昂人不得進入帝國的領土
Anacreons aren't allowed on imperial soil.
你來這里做什么
What are you doing here?
拾荒
Scrapping.
很少看見拾荒者披盔戴甲
That's a lot of armor for scrappers.
我們在找這艘船的導航模組
We're looking for the ship's navigation module.
這艘廢船上的任何關鍵部件 早在數十年前就被拆走了
Any critical components were stripped from this hulk decades ago.
不過一位真正的拾荒者會知道這點
But, again, a real scrapper would know that.
你應該離開 趁帝國還未得知此事
You should leave. Before the Empire catches wind of this.
我族人并不畏懼帝國
My people do not fear the Empire.
聽著 你們沒想到會碰到我
Look, I caught you by surprise
所以你們在臨時想辦法
and now you're improvising.
但如果你們要殺我 你們早就動手了
But if you were gonna kill me, you would have already.
接下來的計劃是
So what's the play?
那座塔 帶我們去那里
That tower. Take us there.
為什么
Why?
我還是說清吧 守衛者
Let me be clear, Warden.
我們知道如何利用一切可用的資源
We know how to use every resource we come across.
我們早前觀察那幾個孩子
The children we observed earlier,
我們看到他們在黎明前夕偷偷溜走
we've seen how they sneak away just before dawn,
遠離了你們其他人
straying far away from the rest of your flock.
如果你不帶我們去那座塔 我們只需利用其中一個孩子就行 很簡單
If you won't lead us to the tower, we'll simply utilize one of them.
沒那么簡單 那里有圍欄
It's not that simple. We have a fence.
我們知道你們有圍欄
We're aware of your fence.
我們看到你之前在那里進行維護工作
We saw you perform maintenance on it earlier.
所以你是帶我們穿越圍欄的完美人選
Which makes you the perfect person to take us through it.
那就去塔那里吧
To the tower then!
我們在圍欄上使用了基因識別技術
The fence uses DNA recognition.
任何不在數據庫里的人都會被輻射擊中
It'll radiate anyone who isn't in the database.
我可以帶一個人進去
I might be able to get one of you in.
如果我們一起穿越
If we walk through together,
圍欄會將第二人視作系統錯誤
the fence should write off the second person as an error.
那就帶我們所有人進去
Then take us all through it.
這招只能用一次 可能吧
This only works once. Maybe.
我過去曾拖進圍欄的生物已經死了
The only thing I've ever dragged through this fence was already dead.
我能感到你的緊張 別緊張
I can feel you tensing up. Don't.
如果她在這一輪值班結束前沒回來 我們會夷平你的城市
If she isn't back within a watch, we'll raze your city to the ground.
去 叫上其他人
Go. Get the others.
建立一個防線 別讓人看見
Establish a perimeter and stay out of sight.
你來駕駛 我拿槍
Wanna drive and I'll hold the gun?
至少告訴我你的名字吧
Tell me your name, at least.
我們成了好朋友了
Are we best friends now?
你冒很大的險來這里
You've risked a lot coming here.
我們賭上了一切 守衛者
We've risked everything, Warden.
-不 前方路上有個男孩 -別耍花招 我有眼睛
-No. There was a boy in our path! -Don't get cute. I have eyes.
塔在那邊
The tower's that way.
這是捷徑 這條路的守衛比較少
I'm taking a shortcut. Fewer watchmen this way.
那是什么
What is that?
停下
Stop.
關于塞佛哈定的那些傳說  通常從這里開始
The stories about Salvor Hardin? They usually begin here.
守衛者與幽靈
The warden and the ghost,
令人費解地緊密聯系在一起
inexplicably bound together.
謝謝
Thanks.
他們是怎么避開我們的雷達的
How did they slip past our radar?
也許是按低空航線飛進來的
Flew in the nap of the earth. Maybe.
有他們飛船的蹤跡嗎
Any sign of their ships?
他們自稱為拾荒者 說他們在找導航模組
They claimed to be scrappers. Said they were after a navigation module.
-明顯的謊言 -我們必須聯絡帝國
-Obviously bullshit. -We need to contact the Empire.
未經授權 我們不能做任何事
We can't do anything without authorization.
拜托 媽媽 我們只是名義上的帝國哨站
Come on, Mom. We're an imperial outpost in name only.
他們上一次聯絡我們是哪年哪月  十年前了吧
When was the last time they even contacted us? A decade ago?
他們不會保護我們的 我們必須自己來
They won't defend us. We need to do it ourselves.
別急 暴力是無能者…
Easy. Violence is the last refuge--
最后的庇護所 我知道 那是老人之言
Of the incompetent, I know. That's an old man's doctrine.
那是我比你更年輕時觀察所得的道理
It's an observation I made when I was younger than you.
在哈里的計劃中 我們會等待幫助還是獨立行動
Would Hari's plan have assumed we'd wait for help or act on our own?
哈里已經不在這了 媽媽 我們必須自救
Hari is not here, Mom. We need to help ourselves.
歡迎醒來 我的好朋友
Welcome back, best friend.
我們正要加深對彼此的了解時你就昏迷了
You left the conversation just as we were really getting to know each other.
頭疼 感覺牙齒要掉了
Headache? Teeth feel like they're falling out?
那該死的東西是什么
What was that cursed thing?
我們對端點星殖民時它就在了
It was here when we colonized Terminus.
我們在掃描時沒探測到它 我猜你們也沒有
Didn't show up on any of our scans. I guess it didn't show up on yours either.
為什么你沒有受影響
Why did it not affect you?
只能說我是你在端點星上最不想碰到的人
Let's just say I'm the last person on Terminus you wanted to come across.
所以…
So…
然后呢 守衛者
what now, Warden?
她帶了一支小規模軍隊
She had a small army with her.
還有他們的腳印 有的很深
An-- And their tracks, some of them were deep.
步幅較短 好像他們在搬運沉重的設備
Shorter stride lengths. As if they were carrying heavy equipment.
他們似乎計劃在此駐留 爸爸
Like they're planning on digging in, Dad.
-你想怎么做  -不知道
-Well, what do you wanna do? -I don't know.
我一直遵從我的直覺 但…
I've been following my instincts, and--
我不知道 也許那只是碰巧走運
I don't know, maybe it was just dumb luck.
你的直覺不僅僅帶你上了飛船
Your instincts didn't just lead you to the ships.
而且讓你找到了她 你阻止了她
They led you to her. And you stopped her.
如果你數學更好的話
If you were better at math,
你就會知道反復而來的運氣 就絕不僅是運氣 塞佛
you'd know that repeated luck was more than just luck, Salvor.
無論你母親是否愿意承認
Whether your mother wants to admit it or not,
自從你學會走路起 我們一直跟著你的行為做事
we have been following your lead from the moment you pulled yourself upright.
人們選你擔任守衛者是有原因的
It's no accident the people made you warden.
所以 帶領我們吧
So lead us.
很榮幸初次見到您 大帝 有何可為您效勞
I have never had the pleasure, Empire. How may I be of service?
你是歐布雷特隊長
Captain Obrecht, is it?
陰影師 大帝 陰影師歐布雷特
Shadowmaster, Empire. Shadowmaster Obrecht.
非常相像
A fine likeness.
處理有問題的宮殿人員 規程是什么
What's the protocol for dealing with a problem palace attendant?
請問是哪個級別的人員
What level of attendant, if I may ask?
-在花園工作的人 -我能問是哪類問題嗎
-Someone who works in the garden. -May I ask the nature of the problem?
不能 我只需要她的名字
You may not. I just want her name.
沒問題 大帝 若還需要什么 也可以交代我
I can ascertain that, Empire. Along with anything else you may require.
暫時只有這個
That's all for now.
我看到圍欄外至少有十幾個安納克里昂人
I saw at least a dozen Anacreons outside the fence.
特拉維克 從南邊的環圈靠近
Travik, take the southern loop.
凱林 你負責西邊
Kalin, cover the west.
葉特 你守在東邊 監控有沒有人從那個山脊過來
Yate, I want you on the east so you can spot anyone coming over that ridge.
如果看到那些人 我們該做什么
And if we see any of these guys, what are we supposed to do?
什么都不做
Nothing.
別向他們開槍 別跟他們說話 觀察他們 隨時向我匯報情況
Don't shoot at them, don't speak to them. Just watch 'em and keep me informed.
-端點星出現安納克里昂人是怎么回事  -她叫法拉
-What's this about Anacreons on Terminus? -Calls herself Phara.
除此之外 她的故事完全說不通
Beyond that, nothing about her story adds up.
你最擅長看出別人是否在撒謊了
If anyone can tell whether somebody's lying, it's you.
問題就是這個 我看不出她在撒謊
That's just the thing. I can't tell if she's lying
還是不說實情
or if she's just not telling the truth.
兩者有差別嗎
Is there a difference?
我有個計劃 但我需要你的幫助
I've got a plan. But I'm gonna need your help.
這是做什么 虐囚
What's this? Torture?
他是我的男仆從
He's my manservant.
為我跑腿 在需要的時候幫我的靴子封邊
Runs and fetches. Reseals my boots when they need it.
我猜對我野外的同伴來說 這一輪值班已經結束了
I'm thinking a watch has passed, as far as my weald-men are concerned.
你到底為何來這里 法拉
Why are you really here, Phara?
塞佛很擅長讀人心
Salvor has a talent for reading people.
準得嚇人 我剛才還和她母親聊起
It's uncanny, really. I was just telling her mother about it.
她不相信你
She doesn't believe you.
你剛告訴她你是我的上司 這下我像在拍馬屁了
Well, you told her you're my boss. Now my praise rings hollow.
你對基地塔為何感興趣
What's your interest in the Foundation Tower?
因為模組 我已經告訴你了 你總是問我相同的問題
The module. I already told you. You keep asking me the same questions.
我是在給你機會 讓你回答得更好
I'm giving you a chance to give better answers.
正面
Crowns.
我知道你在找別的東西
I know you're after something else.
我們沒有任何安納克里昂文物 也沒有重型武器 所以到底…
We don't have any Anacreon artifacts, no heavy weapons, so what--
我們在原地繞圈
This is going in circles.
解釋給她聽
Explain it to her.
把她想要的給她吧
Just give her what she wants.
你的口音不算糟
Your accent's not terrible.
你顯然是向港口城市的人學的
You were taught by someone in the port city, obviously.
懶元音
Those lazy vowels.
我是貿易商
I'm a trader.
我偶爾與你們星球的人做生意
I do business with your people now and then.
怪不得從你身上 我嗅到了狄斯比斯人的味道
Thought I smelled a whiff of Thespin on you.
我要導航模組 僅此而已
I want the navigation module. That's it.
又是一個謊言
Another lie.
你也說安納克里昂語
You speak Anacreon as well?
一個字都不懂
Not a word.
-但你知道我在撒謊  -反面
-Yet you know I'm lying? -Cats.
概率是二分之一
That was a 50-50 chance.
又是反面 你到底是誰
Cats again. Who are you really?
概率是四分之一
Twenty-five percent chance there.
又回到正面了
Now it's back to crowns.
八分之一了 又一個正面 你為什么來這里
Twelve and a half percent. And another crown. Why are you here?
又是正面
Another crown again.
我可以把概率告訴你 但是反復而來的運氣絕不是運氣
I'd give you the percentage, but repeated luck is never luck.
你是誰
Who are you?
我們是拾荒者 為找模組而來
We're scrappers. The module.
你們不是拾荒者 導航模組不過是為了轉移…
You're not scrappers. And the navigation module's a distraction--
別再玩這些幼稚的把戲了
Enough of these child games.
把這個狄斯比斯暴徒的鏈子解開 讓他直接動手吧
Take this Thespin thug off his leash and let him get on with it!
你的疤痕…
Your scars…
蟹足腫
keloids.
你的左眼…
Your left eye…
納米玻璃
nano-glass.
你是在帝國轟炸安納克里昂時 失去左眼的吧
You lose it when the Empire bombed Anacreon?
你當時應該是五、六歲
I imagine you must have been, what, five, six at the time?
中子彈的爆發力較低 但是電離輻射的能量很高
Neutron bombs have a low explosive yield but a high amount of ionizing radiation.
我知道大約一半的人口一周內就死去了
Now, I know about 50% of the population died off within a week,
另外的兩、三成人在那一年里死去
another 20 or 30 within the remaining year.
你很可能在那次轟炸后 成為孤兒了 對吧
Odds are you came out the other end an orphan, right?
也許失去了爸媽
Probably lost a mom and dad.
活活地被燒死
Boiled alive.
也許是慢性死亡
Or maybe s-slower.
癌癥
Cancer.
你的母親是甲狀腺癌 她的嗓音在死前變了
Thyroid for your mother. Her voice, it changed before she died.
你還失去了誰 姐妹
Who else did you lose? A sister?
一個兄弟
A brother.
一個弟弟
A little brother.
她的內心有一種死亡的氣息 就像…
There's a deadness inside her. It's like a--
沒有底的井 將一切吸入
It's like a well with no bottom, just sucking everything in.
她想死
She wants to die.
她想讓所有人死 我感覺到了
She wants everyone to die. I felt it.
她在崩潰時說了什么 你聽懂了嗎
What she said when she broke, did you understand any of it?
聽懂了一些 是古安納克里昂語 不是通用語
Some, yeah. It's archaic Anacreon, not the common vernacular.
她說漏嘴了 因為我也聽懂了一些話
Well, she slipped up. Because I understood something too.
一個我曾在全息影像見過的名字 拉肯柯恩
A name I remember from the holos. Larken Keaen.
在安鐸星帶糾紛事件時
During the Anthor Belt dispute,
安納克里昂和狄斯比斯為帝國帶去貢禮
Anacreon and Thespis brought gifts to the Emperor.
我族人帶的是《洗禮經》
My people's was the Book of Ablut--
安納克里昂的是一把 為其最偉大獵手雕刻的弓
And Anacreon's was a bow carved for its greatest hunter.
-拉肯柯恩 -意思是
-Larken Keaen. -Meaning?
法拉不是什么撿垃圾的
Phara's not just some junker.
她是安納克里昂的大獵手
She's the Grand Huntress of Anacreon.
這一切動亂到底是誰造成的
All this unrest, who's responsible for it?
墮落者 這是一個化名
Sinkers. A nom de guerre.
77層的熱沉室熔化后 那是星橋墜落造成的
After the heat sink meltdown on level 77. It was caused when the Star Bridge fell.
35年后 我們仍在處理這件事的余波
And 35 years later we're still grappling with the aftereffects.
大帝的職責就是 處理一堆相互競爭優先級的事項
The businesses of Empire is a cascade of competing priorities.
我和主教團會面時 白晝兄弟將會需要你的幫助
Brother Day will need your support while I tend to the conclave.
公務太繁多
It's overwhelming.
對于一個人而言
For one man.
幸運的是我們有三個人
Fortunately, there are three of us.
壞事往往成三 你聽說了嗎 兄弟
Bad tidings also come in threes. Have you heard the news, Brother?
大角星區有一個通訊浮標斷聯了
A communications buoy in the Arcturus Sector has come off-line.
那些浮標應該常常斷聯吧
They must go off-line all the time, right?
我們大概有幾千個浮標遍布整個星系
We probably have thousands of them across the galaxy.
數萬個
Tens of thousands.
但只有那個浮標負責外圍星域的通訊
But only one that handles communications in the Outer Reach.
你沒有理解此事的嚴重性
I see that you fail to grasp the significance.
是端點星
It's Terminus.
黃昏兄弟將哈里謝頓的信徒流放到那里
It's where Brother Dusk exiled Hari Seldon's followers.
外圍星域、主教團、叛變
The Reach. The conclave. Insurgency…
你看出這一系列事情的規律了嗎
Do you see a pattern forming here?
給他們看看
Show them.
感知到你們的脆弱后 很快將有其他力量 開始對帝國進行破壞
Sensing vulnerability, soon other players will begin to apply downward pressure.
銀河中某個主要的宗教必然會發起煽動
An exhortation from one of the galaxy's major religions is a given.
也可能是川陀本地發起的起義
Or perhaps a homegrown insurrection here on Trantor.
如果滅亡的速度可以加快 那可以減慢嗎
If the fall can be accelerated, can it not also be slowed?
瞧瞧你現在 兄弟
Now look at you, Brother.
坐在中央王座上 剛愎自用的樣子
So smugly self-assured atop the middle throne.
我以前會在鏡子前練習這個笑容
I used to practice that smile in the mirror.
夠了 我知道這一幕的結局
Enough. I know how the scene ends.
但你領會了其中的教訓嗎
But have you embraced its lessons?
透光教 如今墮落者起義了
Luminism. The Sinker insurrection happening now.
謝頓幾乎給你列了一份待做事項清單
Seldon all but drew you a to-do list.
你卻完全無視
And you ignored him.
因為他是個江湖騙子
Because he was a charlatan.
你沒有任何新的創造
You offer nothing new.
不過是一個更嫩的葡萄
Just a younger grape…
來自同一個葡萄藤
from the same vine,
注定釀成同樣的酒
destined for the same old bottle.
你們無法拯救自己
You can't save yourselves…
但你們能拯救功業 傳承后世
but you can save your legacy.
哈里謝頓已死去多時
Hari Seldon is long dead.
而且是被自己的學徒殺死的
Murdered by his protégé, no less.
人是死了 但是阻止得了起義嗎 兄弟
The man was murdered. But what about the movement, Brother?
烈士的影響力往往超越其本身的生命長度
Martyrs tend to have a long half-life.
因為你 我們所看到的是 一個真正的外交危機的開始
Thanks to you, we are now staring down the barrel of a genuine diplomatic crisis.
我該做什么 路易斯
What was I supposed to do, Lewis?
讓法拉殺了我 然后對孩子們動手
Let Phara kill me and then move on to the kids?
你不該在我不在場的情況下拷問她
You shouldn't have questioned her without me.
你應慶幸 我們知道她的身份了
Be glad I did. We know who she is now.
我們有籌碼了 可以與她的同伴討價還價
We have leverage. We can bargain with her people.
如果這個選擇讓全城陷入暴動
If this choice inflames the city into violence,
你成功讓我們如此高明地自取滅亡
you have achieved elaborate suicide for us all.
哈里不是說基地會在 第一次危機中存活嗎
Didn't Hari say the Foundation survives the first crisis?
沒錯 但正如我曾告訴你的 你是異類
Yes, he did. But, as I've told you before, you are an outlier.
-意思是  -塞佛
-Meaning? -Salvor.
意思是計算結果不包括你
Meaning that you weren't accounted for.
你與穹窿有一種聯結
You have a connection with the Vault
而那是不可能被預測的
which couldn't have possibly have been predicted.
模型中沒有你
You are not baked into the model.
意思是我不屬于上帝的計劃
You're saying I'm not part of God's plan.
意思是心理歷史學無法計算個人行為
I am saying psychohistory can't account for individuals.
所以你是說我毀了上帝的計劃
So you're saying I've destroyed God's plan?
-是時候后退一步了 塞佛 -退一步
-It's time to take a step back, Salvor. -Step back?
我以為基地存在的全部意義
I thought the whole damn point of the Foundation
在于為難以預料的情況做準備
was preparing for the unthinkable.
在我要求更多防御武器時
When I asked for more defensive weapons,
你說襲擊的可能性極低
you said the likelihood of an attack seemed remote.
在我提出進行更多軍事訓練時 沒人回應
When I wanted to run more drills, nothing.
結果我們走到這一步 毫無準備
So here we are now, not prepared.
也許我是異類 但搞砸計劃的不是我 路易斯
I might be an outlier, but I'm not the one screwing up the Plan, Lewis.
這是總督路易斯皮仁恩
Lewis Pirenne, director.
安納克里昂議事會為什么派最高級的軍官
Now, why would the Anacreon Council send its highest-ranking military officer
到一個帝國哨站
to an imperial outpost?
這是你們的末日邪教偽裝出來的門面嗎
Is that what you're pretending your little doomsday cult is?
因為我在這里看不見帝國的影子
Because I don't see the Empire anywhere.
我只看到學者、勞工和極少的槍械
All I see are academics, laborers and very few guns.
你們破壞了通訊浮標
You took down the comms buoy.
當然 我們想暗中行動 避開監控
Of course. We wanted to operate in private, away from prying eyes.
你要明白帝國最終會派人來調查的
You have to know the Empire will send someone to investigate eventually.
還是說那就是你的意圖
Or is that the point?
你們這里的女性比男性聰明多了
Your women are so much sharper than your men.
蠻族王國被流放了 你們沒有理由來這里
The barbarian kingdoms are exiled. You have no business here.
“蠻族”
"Barbarians."
不過是個用在異類身上的 歧視詞語 真是方便
Just a convenient slur for anyone not like you.
川陀讓我們在這里自生自滅 你的人和我的人
Trantor left us all here to die. Your people and mine.
我們不過是以不同的速度滅亡
We're just dying at different speeds.
基地沒有滅亡
The Foundation isn't dying.
我們要完成哈里謝頓托付我們的任務
We are fulfilling the mission Hari Seldon entrusted us with.
謝頓也預測到滅亡將會從銀河邊緣開始
Seldon also predicted that the fall would begin at the edge of the galaxy.
-這里 -同樣的科學計算
-Here. -The same science
在星橋墜落時拯救了帝國宮殿
that saved the Imperial Palace when the Star Bridge fell
也保護著端點市
protects Terminus City.
你是說你的能量屏障
You mean your energy barrier?
武器的效用取決于使用者的能耐
A weapon's only as good as the man who's wielding it.
凱林 你那邊情況如何
Kalin, what's your situation?
這里的人越來越多了
It's getting pretty crowded over here.
-我可能需要支援 -不可能
-I think I need backup. -Not happening.
塞佛看到十幾個人 你是說 到處都是安納克里昂人
Salvor saw a dozen. You're telling me we've got Anacreons all over?
我是說我看到他們攜帶的槍械 足以將整座城夷為平地
I'm telling you I'm seeing enough guns to take out the whole town.
大帝
Empire.
我們討論的問題
The matter we discussed?
她叫阿祖拉歐蒂利 13歲起成為宮殿植物學家
Her name is Azura Odili. A palace botanist since the age of 13.
她的父親已身故 生前也是花園的農業生態學家
Her father, deceased, was also an agroecologist in the gardens.
她的母親創辦了一所插花學校 目前已關閉了
Her mother founded a school for the ikebana, now closed.
你是說有什么問題嗎
You said there was a problem?
在這種情況下通常怎么解決問題
How are problems generally solved in this situation?
只要能達到目的就可以 我的職責是讓問題消失 大帝
Any manner that achieves its goal. My job is to eliminate problems, Empire.
阿祖拉歐戴利
Azura Odili.
歐迪利 歐德利
Oh-dee-lee? Oh-dih-lee?
蒂 大帝
Dee, Empire.
你之前在我的寢宮外
You were outside my chambers earlier.
-我想知道你認為自己看見了什么 -我什么都沒看見 大帝
-Want to know what you think you saw. -I saw nothing, Empire.
不 我認為你看見了一些東西
No. I believe you saw something.
我只看見大帝希望我看見的
I only see what Empire wants me to see.
我可以罷免你的職務
I could have you removed from your station,
送你去80層清理熱沉室
sent to scrub the heat sinks on level 80.
我可以對你下狠手 遠比這更狠
I could do worse to you. Much worse.
你很清楚
You know all this.
大帝 黃昏兄弟讓我來請你過去
Empire, Brother Dusk has asked me to summon you.
告訴他我馬上過去
Tell him I'm coming.
把這個花圃都移除
Remove this entire bed.
在我的寢宮 花的香氣太濃郁了
From my chambers the smell of the blossoms is overbearing.
-大帝 這種事不需要你… -已經解決了 你走吧
-Empire, you needn't bother with this-- -It's settled. You can go.
狼息葉有助緩解疼痛
Wolvesbreath helps with the pain.
是帶紅色條紋的褐綠色葉子
The brownish-green leaves with the red stripe.
它們能緩解腫脹和淤傷…
They reduce the swelling and bruising--
我不記得向你征求醫療建議
I don't recall asking for your medical advice.
是哪種
Which?
尖葉
The pointed leaves.
這是什么
What is it?
狼靈屬
Lupi spiritus.
這是狼息葉 大帝 來自我們的草藥園
Wolvesbreath, Empire. From our medicinal garden.
是一種鎮痛劑和血管舒張藥
It's an analgesic and vasodilator.
有毒嗎
Is it poisonous?
沒有 狼息葉可以泡茶或釀藥酒
No. Wolvesbreath is used in tea as well as tinctures.
它能刺激血管、促進康復…
It stimulates the blood vessels, promotes healing--
吃下去
Eat it.
如果接下來的幾個小時你沒死
If you're not dead within the next few hours,
就送1公斤到我的寢宮來
have a kilogram of these sent to my quarters.
是 大帝
Of course, Empire.
雷洛弗拉姆 馬上回家
Laylo Fulham, get your ass back home this instant!
他們會突破嗎
Are they gonna get through?
當然不會
Course not.
大家都回家去 拜托了 這里不安全 快后退…
Go back to your home, people. Please. It's not safe out here. Back up. Back up.
你們必須立即離開
You need to come out here. Now.
我挺忙的 葉特
Kind of busy here, Yate.
我知道 但我還是要打給你
I know, and I'm still calling.
安納克里昂軍隊在東邊、西邊、南邊集結
We've got Anacreon's troops massing from the east, west, south,
估計北邊也有
and presumably the north.
還記得怎么拿槍嗎 老頭
Remember how to hold a rifle, old man?
槍管對著前方
Barrel goes forward?
我們在圍欄外的多個地點 發現安納克里昂人
We've spotted Anacreons at multiple locations outside the fence.
-我去西邊 -我們去北邊
-I'll go west. -We'll head north.
我不應該離開 路易斯完全不是對手
I shouldn't leave. Lewis is completely overmatched in there.
我會照顧他的 我保證
I'll babysit him, I promise.
好吧
All right.
是真的嗎 里面有安納克里昂的頭目
Is it true? You got some kind of Anacreon chieftain in there?
你喝酒了嗎 穆勒
You been drinking, Muller?
銀河系要完蛋了 是嗎  哈里的預測成真了
It's the end of the galaxy, isn't it? Hari's prediction's coming true.
你聽到的是謠言 穆勒 只是一個本地的盜獵者
You got hold of a bad rumor, Muller. Local poacher's all.
他們已經到了 對吧
They're already here, aren't they?
嘿 不如你歇一下吧
Hey, why don't you just take a break for a second.
嘿
Hey!
我不會傷害你的
I won't hurt you.
告訴我你是誰
Just tell me who you are.
塞
Sal.
塞 嘿…怎么回事
Sal. Hey, hey. What's wrong?
我剛才在川陀的帝國圖書館
I was just in the Imperial Library on Trantor.
-什么叫你在那里  -我身處那里 在書架間
-What do you mean you were there? -I mean I was there. In the stacks.
天花板是木制的 還有很多大理石半身像
The ceiling was wooden, there were all these marble busts.
有個拿著刀的男孩
And there was a boy with a knife.
是帶我找到安納克里昂人的那個男孩
It was the same boy who led me to the Anacreons.
是穹窿 我能感覺到它 雨果 它想告訴我些什么
It's the Vault. I can feel it, Hugo. It's trying to tell me something
關于安納克里昂人和這次危機 關于一切
about the Anacreons and this crisis. Everything.
好的 聽我說 我過去總說 你應該離開這個星球
Okay, listen to me. I've always said you should let this planet shrug you off.
但看到你做的事 你竟能感知 法拉內心的想法
But watching you work, where you could sense what Phara was feeling inside…
這很特別
that's special.
塞 別的人不可能做到這點
Other people can't do that, Sal.
我對你有百分之百的信心
I have absolute faith in you.
你們中的誰是統計學大師提沃爾
Who among you is Master Statistician Tivole?
大帝 愿明光永不滅
Empire. May the light never dim.
愿明光永不滅
May the light never dim.
-你收到我的征詢了 -是 大帝
-You received my query. -I did, Empire.
但我們尚未得到結果
But I can't say yet we have the results.
黃昏給你安排這項任務后已經過了多久
How long has it been since Dusk set you to this task?
30年
Three decades?
你在你那數字陵墓里都忙些什么
What do you do in your mausoleum of calculus
為何還沒有結果
if not achieve results?
那就說進展吧 你有何進展
Progress, then. What is your progress?
我們認為哈里謝頓的預測模型 是違背事實的
We believe the-- the predictive models of Hari Seldon to be counterfactual.
為什么這么說
And you believe this why?
在謝頓發表他的異教學說后的35年來
In the 35 years since Seldon uttered his heretical proclamations,
帝國擴張了 而不是收縮 無論是以哪個重要的參數…
the Imperium has expanded, rather than contracted, by every critical metric--
夠了
Stop.
謝頓的預言
Seldon's prophecies.
和我說說他的數學計算 這個“序數分析”
Speak to me of his math, this "ordinal analysis."
不過是一幅占卜牌
It's a spread of fortune teller's cards
謝頓選擇將其詮釋為神旨
which Seldon chose to interpret as divination.
他在回歸模型中發現的證明 并沒有證據所支持
The verification he found in the regression models is unsupported.
但是近期的種種事件怎么說
But what of these-- these recent events?
主教團 透光教
The conclave? Luminism?
毫無根據的猜想 同樣是模糊而沒有證據支持的
Baseless conjecture. Again, vague and unsupported.
任何人都能預測到回到正教這件事
I mean, anyone could predict a return to orthodoxy.
心理歷史學只是老人空想出來的研究
Psychohistory is the fanciful work of an old man's imagination.
如果它并非老人空想出來的研究 那么是什么
If it weren't the fanciful work of an old man's imagination, what then?
研究最終被證為真實的概率是多少
What is the likelihood that it's all true? Every prophecy?
微小得可以忽略 大帝
Vanishingly small, Empire.
但不是零
But not zero.
對嗎
Correct?
非零
Not zero?
你們到底是什么白癡
What kind of idiots are you?
一千個帝國數學家
A thousand imperial mathematicians…
卻理解不了一個人的計算
…can't parse the numbers of one man?
所以銀河系中沒有任何人有辦法
So there's nothing anyone in the galaxy can do?
這是你們交出的最佳結果
Is that what it is? Is that the best you've got?
告訴我…
Tell me. Tell me!
告訴我
Tell me!
在人生的晚年
In the twilight of a man's life…
當他的個人歷史將近尾聲時
…when his biography is nearly complete,
他開始絕望地想知道他的人生
he grows desperate to know the measure of his days…
他的聲音與前人所有的聲音相比結果如何
how his voice compares to the chorus of those who've come before.
我重要嗎 我的選擇是自己做出的嗎
Do I matter? Are my choices my own?
我的命運是否被看不見的手所左右
Or is my destiny governed by an unseen hand?
白晝兄弟 來為我們送行
Brother Day. Come to see us off?
你的統計師們來找過我
I was paid a visit by your statisticians.
他們的計算結果如此自圓其說 真了不起
It's remarkable how self-reinforcing their results are.
我認為你最好還是留在川陀處理事務
I think it's best that you stay and tend to matters on Trantor.
大帝 第一克里昂從未離開過川陀
Empire, a primary Cleon has not left the bosom of Trantor
從一脈相承的王朝開始起就沒有過
since the dawn of the Genetic Dynasty.
德默澤爾是對的
Demerzel is right.
我們訂立這些規程是有原因的
We have these protocols in place for a reason.
我則認為我們的規程讓我們懈怠了
And I say our protocols have made us complacent.
當年你和我現在一樣坐在中央王座上
When you sat on the middle throne, as I do now,
討論如何處理安納克里昂和狄斯比斯時
and were debating what to do about Anacreon and Thespis,
我們該如何回應 你記得 你當時是怎么說的嗎
what our response should be, do you remember what you said?
記得
I do.
仿佛是昨日
Like it was yesterday.
那時我七歲
I was seven.
我們最年長的兄弟認為應該恩赦
Our eldest brother had argued for a bout of grace.
你轉向我說 “你如何看此事 初升的黎明 ”
You turned to me and said, "What do you think, Ascending Dawn?"
我知道你反對恩赦
I knew you were against grace,
你想轟炸蠻族王國
that you wanted to bomb the barbarian kingdoms.
但我很怕 我大膽說了出來
But I was scared. And I dared say so.
如今我已經不怕了
Well, I'm not scared anymore.
在你的統治下 星橋墜落 在那件事的傷疤上 人們掀起起義
On your watch, the Star Bridge fell. And from that scar insurgency was birthed.
在你的統治下 兩個世界燒為灰燼
On your watch, two worlds were incinerated
完全不顧及無辜者或后果
with not a care to innocence or consequence.
在你的統治下 哈里謝頓和他的信眾得以逃離
On your watch, Hari Seldon and his followers were allowed to flee.
你把一個因為任性妄為 而四分五裂的帝國交到我手上
You have bequeathed me an Empire rent by impulsive action.
我不會重蹈覆轍 在我的統治下不會這樣
The same will not be said of me. Not on my watch.
我將拯救我們的功業
I would save our legacy.
兄弟
Brother…
一個早已死去的人 陰魂不散 令你無法釋懷
you are haunted by the ghost of a man long dead.
我們都是如此 兄弟
We all are, Brother.
你的統治已經結束
Your watch is over.
你將留在川陀 處理你放任不管 而因此惡化的傷口
You will stay on Trantor, tending to the wounds you have allowed to fester.
走吧
Go.
把黃昏兄弟的物品送回宮殿
Return Brother Dusk's belongings to the palace.
如今帝國當然不會因莽撞行事而分崩離析
Certainly now the Empire will no longer be rent by impulsive action.
是你召喚我嗎 大帝
You summoned me, Empire?
外圍星域的一個通訊浮標斷聯了
A communications buoy has gone dark in the Outer Reach.
帶上你的團隊去調查
Take your team and investigate.
這就去 大帝
At once, Empire.
多爾文
Dorwin.
基地通訊的頻率越來越少了
Our dispatches from the Foundation have become sporadic.
去造訪他們
Pay them a visit.
提醒基地 不要對帝國有所隱瞞
And remind the Foundation that Empire will not be kept in the dark.
-那是… -情況不太妙 是吧
-Is that, uh-- -Doesn't look good, does it?
這里由誰指揮 路易斯還是你  還是玩硬幣的守衛者
Who is in charge here, Lewis? You? Or is it the Warden with the coin tricks?
因為她似乎讓情況變得復雜了
Because it seems she's managed to complicate matters.
-讓我說清楚 獵手柯恩 -大獵手
-Let me be clear, Huntress Keaen-- -Grand Huntress.
我們面臨危機的唯一原因
The only reason we have a crisis
是你們擅自入侵帝國的私人領域
is because you trespassed on the Emperor's personal domain.
如果塞佛當時帶我去塔那邊 把我要的東西給我
If only Salvor had taken me to the tower and given me what I'd wanted,
我們早都離開這個星球了
we'd already be off-planet.
我們慢速艦上的模組
The module from our slow ship?
你們的人又不會用它
It's not as if your people have any use for it.
你們已經困在端點星了 帝國確保這一點
You're marooned on Terminus. The Empire made sure of that.
路易斯
Lewis.
你們為何需要模組
Why do you need it?
我族人在科技上極其匱乏
My people are technologically bankrupt.
我們要滅亡了 總督
We're dying, Director.
自從帝國讓我們的大氣層燃燒后 我們一直苦苦掙扎
We have been ever since the Empire set our atmosphere on fire.
因為一個并非我們犯下的罪行 一半人口失去生命
Half our population lost for a crime that we were innocent of.
和你們不同 我們有飛船
Unlike you, we have ships.
我們能夠離開被摧毀的世界 尋找另一個恒星系
We can leave our poisoned world, find another star system.
我們只需要在虛空中導航的工具
If only we had the means to navigate the void.
如果支援你們 帝國會摧毀我們
The Empire would crush us for assisting you.
我們這是在逼你出手相助 總督
We're forcing your hand, Director.
因為我們已經沒什么可失去的了
Because we have nothing left to lose.
你無法和一個愿意將棋盤燒毀的人下棋
You can't play chess with someone who's willing to set the board on fire.
那是某種高射炮嗎
Is that some kind of flak cannon?
如果他們以為那能突破圍欄 那就是在浪費時間
Wasting their time if they think that's gonna penetrate the fence.
這一切都不對勁 法拉應該更高明的
None of this feels right. Phara is smarter than this.
他們摧毀了通訊浮標 他們是有備而來
They took out the comms buoy, and they came in prepared.
他們的策略比我們想的大 但我卻看不出到底是什么
There's a larger strategy here, and I am missing it somehow.
不如我乘飛船離開 去其他星球求助
What if I take my ship, make a run for the stars, get help?
不行…你還沒進入軌道 就會被他們從空中擊落
No, no. They'd shoot you out of the sky before you ever made it into orbit.
后悔沒在還來得及的時候離開了
Regretting you didn't bug out when you had the chance?
我這輩子做的傻事多了去了 塞佛哈定
Done a lot of foolish things in my life, Salvor Hardin.
陪在你身邊不是其中之一
Sticking by your side is not one of them.
史上最佳男仆從
Best manservant ever.
穹窿并非出自安納克里昂之手
The Vault isn't Anacreon…
也不是外星生物建的
or alien at all.
它一定與哈里有關
It's gotta be connected to Hari.
你怎么知道
How do you know that?
因為我昏迷時看到的畫面
Because the vision I saw when I blacked out,
是川陀星 在哈里的圖書館 有個男孩拿刀指著我
it was on Trantor in Hari's library, with a boy holding a knife on me.
也許這是在警告我們遠離它
What if it was a warning to stay away?
如果路易斯是對的呢
What if Lewis is right?
正如他所說的 我是異類 橫沖直撞、四處搗亂
I'm an outlier, just like he says, barging around, knocking things over,
搞砸了謝頓的計劃
screwing up Seldon's plan?
塞佛 如果你就是謝頓的計劃呢
Salvor, what if you are Seldon's plan?
個人的命運將永遠是一個謎
The fate of one individual will always remain a mystery.
守衛者 還記得我的承諾嗎  夷平你的城市
Remember my promise, Warden? Razing your city to the ground?
但一群人的行動
But the movements of masses,
文化的興起與消亡 因果與世界…
the rise and falls of cultures, causes and worlds…
對于這些問題 哈里謝頓早已解開謎底
These were answers Hari Seldon had long since unriddled.
是時候了
It's time.
如其名字所描述的 這場終結的開始
And the beginning of the end, as befitting its name,
在端點星上發生了
took place on Terminus.
字幕翻譯：易晗